<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>openForum</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/</id><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Contact</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/contact.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-09-19:openForumBe/contact.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Information and registration on this site &lt;a href="http://openforum.be/"&gt;http://openforum.be&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Information list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those interested can register to the distribution list (small volume max 1-2 mails per month) 
&lt;a href="mailto:OpenForumInfo@openforum.be"&gt;OpenForumInfo@openforum.be&lt;/a&gt; on
&lt;a href="https://listes.domainepublic.net/listinfo/openforuminfo"&gt;https://listes.domainepublic.net/listinfo/openforuminfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discussion list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People wishing to talk with the other participants can register to the &lt;a href="mailto:discussof@openforum.be"&gt;discussof@openforum.be&lt;/a&gt; mailing list on
&lt;a href="https://listes.domainepublic.net/listinfo/discussof"&gt;https://listes.domainepublic.net/listinfo/discussof&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional information by e-mail and by mail to &lt;a href="mailto:info@openforum.be"&gt;info@openforum.be&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organisation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicolas Pettiaux, &lt;a href="http://www.heb.be/esi"&gt;École supérieure d'informatique (ESI)&lt;/a&gt; et &lt;a href="http://www.ulb.ac.be"&gt;Université libre de Bruxelles (ULB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yves Poullet, &lt;a href="http://www.unamur.be"&gt;Université de Namur (UNamur)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bernard Rentier, &lt;a href="http://www.ulg.ac.be"&gt;Université de Liège (ULG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coordination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Pettiaux &lt;a href="mailto:npettiaux@openforum.be"&gt;npettiaux@openforum.be&lt;/a&gt;, portable : +32 496 24 55 01&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Information</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/information.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-09-19:openForumBe/information.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A meeting and discussion place about the Open, its many variations and
contributions, and related topics : open source, open society , open
data , open education , open innovation , open book , open government ,
open educational resources , open repositories , Researchers
classification ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any interested person, in particular members of universities and
centers of research and teaching in Belgium and abroad, representatives 
and government members, business representatives ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every second Thursday of the month from October to June (except school
holidays) from 18:30 to 21:30 in the University Foundation, rue
d'Egmont 11 , 1000 Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the University Foundation &lt;a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/node/2656942783#map=17/50.83822/4.36697"&gt;11 rue d'Egmont à 1000 Bruxelles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All presentations and materials are in English to facilitate exchanges
between participants from all parts of Belgium and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Program 2015-2106</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/program-2015-2106.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-09-19:openForumBe/program-2015-2106.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 8 October 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Source in healthcare&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/sebastien-jodogne.html"&gt;Sébastien Jodogne&lt;/a&gt; 
 PhD in Computer Science 
(&lt;a href="http://ulg.ac.be"&gt;ULG&lt;/a&gt;) and hospital IT developper from &lt;a href="http://www.chu.ulg.ac.be/internet/"&gt;CHU de Liège&lt;/a&gt;, 
developer of the free software &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt;, 
winner of the &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/news/free-software-award-winners"&gt;FSF 2014 Award for Advancement of Free Software&lt;/a&gt;,
initiator of the &lt;a href="http://osimis.io/"&gt;Osimis&lt;/a&gt; start-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Le logiciel libre dans la santé&lt;/strong&gt; par &lt;a href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/sebastien-jodogne.html"&gt;Sébastien Jodogne&lt;/a&gt; , 
docteur en informatique (&lt;a href="http://ulg.ac.be"&gt;ULG&lt;/a&gt;) et informaticien hospitalier au &lt;a href="http://www.chu.ulg.ac.be/internet/"&gt;CHU de Liège&lt;/a&gt;, 
développeur du logiciel libre &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt;, 
lauréat du &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/news/free-software-award-winners"&gt;prix pour l'avancement du logiciel libre 2014&lt;/a&gt; de la 
&lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org"&gt;Fondation pour le logiciel libre&lt;/a&gt;, initiateur de la start-up  &lt;a href="http://osimis.io/"&gt;Osimis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 12 November 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Education&lt;/strong&gt; par Olivier Bonaventure et Yves Deville professeurs d'inforbyique (UCL), développeur du logiciel liber mptcp et conseiller du recteur pour le numérique, auteur du livre liber CNP3 récompensé par Open-textbook award de Saylor foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 10 December 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open population data for human and animal health&lt;/strong&gt; par 
Marius Gilbert &amp;amp; C. Catherine Linard docteur en science(ULB), FRNS fellow, WUniversity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior Research Associate FNRS (MR) and post-doctoral fellow at ULB &amp;amp;
lecturer in geography at the University of Namur (CL)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 14 January 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Innovation, also in the banks&lt;/strong&gt; par David Dab (*) docteur en sciences (ULB), Innovation manager (ING), MIT fellow, former McKinsey Finance
director.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 10 March 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Access : why so important ?&lt;/strong&gt; par Bernard Rentier (*) docteur en sciences (ULG), recteur honoraire (ULG), président de Open Scholarship, président honoraire du FNRS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 14 April 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Data &amp;amp; copyright reform&lt;/strong&gt; par Pieter Murray-Rust Reader Emeritus , University of Cambridge, Shuttleworth Fellow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 12 May 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open publications &amp;amp; evaluation of researchers and research&lt;/strong&gt; par Pierre-Louis Lions (*) Professeur au Collège de France, académicien, président du conseil d'administration de l'École normale supérieure (Paris)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday 9 June 2015&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Culture&lt;/strong&gt; par Jean-Claude Guédon (*) Professeur à l'Université de Montréal, member de l'Internet Society, auteur du rapport Open Access pour Unesco, conseiller à la Commission européenne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, January 14, 2016 : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Innovation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;as seen in a
bank&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by David Dab (*)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PhD in Sciences (ULB), Innovation manager (ING), MIT postdoctoral fellow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, March 10: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Access, why is it significant for the
Society?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Bernard Rentier&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honorary Rector (ULG), President of OpenScholarship, Honorary President
of the FNRS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, April 14: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Data &amp;amp; copyright reform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by Peter
Murray-Rust&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reader Emeritus, University of Cambridge Fellow &amp;amp; Shuttleworth, running
ContentMine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, May 12 : &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Publications &amp;amp; Researchers Evaluation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by
Pierre-Louis Lions (*)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor at the Collège de France, academician, Président of the École
Normale Superieure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, June 9: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by Jean-Claude Guédon (*)\
 Professor at the University of Montreal, Open Access report writer for
Unesco, advisor to the European Commission&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Registration</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/registration.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-09-19:openForumBe/registration.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The access to the conference is 5 €, payable on site, for the sandwiches and drinks that will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Registration mandatory &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/13DKOzJsRG4VFpN-p2WZE77It07lMktaHI7kaGufevsQ/viewform"&gt;online here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Sébastien Jodogne</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/sebastien-jodogne.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-09-19:openForumBe/sebastien-jodogne.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sébastien Jodogne holds a Ph.D. degree in Computer Science from the 
&lt;a href="http://ulg.ac.be"&gt;University of Liège&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="http://belgium.be"&gt;Belgium&lt;/a&gt;. 
Between 2006 and 2011, he implemented 
high-performance image analysis software for private companies in the 
fields of machine vision, closed-circuit television, and broadcasting. 
Since 2011, he has been working as a medical imaging engineer at the 
&lt;a href="http://www.chu.ulg.ac.be/internet"&gt;University Hospital of Liège&lt;/a&gt;, where he develops the free and open-source 
software &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt;. His research interests include medical imaging, 
computer vision, machine learning and software engineering. His work was 
notably acknowledged by the IBM Belgium Award in 2002, by 
the &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/news/free-software-award-winners"&gt;FSF 2014 Award for Advancement of Free Software&lt;/a&gt;, and by the 
&lt;a href="http://www.agoria.be/en/Liege-University-Hospital-CHU-Liege-wins-the-Agoria-eHealth-Award-for-a-world-first-in-medical-imaging"&gt;Agoria e-Health Award in 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volume of medical images that are generated, analyzed and exchanged 
by hospitals is dramatically increasing. Multimodal medical imaging is 
indeed the first step to the treatment of more and more illnesses, such 
as cancers or cardiovascular diseases. In turn, the data management of 
clinical images and the administration of the computer network of a 
medical imaging department imply continuously growing technological 
challenges. Tasks such as autorouting between imaging modalities, 
exchanging data between clinical departments or hospitals, or 
anonymizing images are still hard to achieve in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will explain these pains of modern medical imaging, 
from the perspective of the hospitals. I will then put emphasis on the 
free and open-source software &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt;, a lightweight, versatile vendor 
neutral archive. &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt; is conceived as a central, robust building 
block to bring technological independence to clinical departments, by 
automating their very specific imaging flows and by creating gateways 
between proprietary ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will conclude by arguing that open standards (such as FHIR and DICOM) 
and their related free and open-source implementations are essential to 
promote interoperability in health care. But, interoperability is at a 
same time a huge opportunity to boost our economical development and to 
protect the freedoms of hospitals and patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contenu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Au cours des vingt dernières années, l’essor puis la démocratisation 
des nouvelles technologies d’imagerie médicale ont mené à de profondes 
révolutions dans la prise en charge clinique de nombreuses pathologies, 
comme le cancer ou l’insuffisance cardiaque. Le volume sans cesse 
croissant d’images auquel tout hôpital est actuellement confronté 
n’est pas sans créer de nombreuses difficultés informatiques : 
acheminement automatique des images depuis les dispositifs 
d’acquisition jusque dans les logiciels d’analyse d’images, 
échanges inter- et extra-hospitaliers, anonymisation des données…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Face à ces besoins impérieux de la collectivité et face au manque 
d’offres commerciales adaptées, le Département de Physique Médicale du 
&lt;a href="http://www.chu.ulg.ac.be/internet"&gt;CHU de Liège&lt;/a&gt; a décidé de concevoir un produit informatique innovant et 
de qualité industrielle. Ce logiciel, nommé &lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt;, est un serveur 
d’imagerie médicale léger, robuste et versatile. Orthanc a la particularité 
d’être un logiciel libre : tous les hôpitaux du monde peuvent donc 
l’utiliser librement, selon une démarche universitaire, collaborative 
et ouverte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L’exemple d’&lt;a href="http://www.orthanc-server.com/"&gt;Orthanc&lt;/a&gt; montre que le logiciel libre permet d’amener 
une meilleure indépendance technologique des services médicaux face 
à leurs fournisseurs. De manière plus générale, les standards ouverts 
du domaine de la santé (tels que FHIR et DICOM) et leurs implémentations 
libres de référence sont des outils essentiels pour créer une 
interopérabilité maximale entre écosystèmes propriétaires dans le 
milieu médical, au bénéfice de notre système de soins de santé. En 
outre, bénéficier d’une telle interopérabilité est une énorme 
opportunité pour stimuler notre tissu industriel en santé électronique, 
ainsi que pour garantir les libertés numériques des patients."&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>