<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>openForum</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/feeds/speakers.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/</id><updated>2015-10-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Yves Deville</title><link href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/yves-deville.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>openForum</name></author><id>tag:npettiaux.github.io,2015-10-08:openForumBe/yves-deville.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yves Deville is full professor at the &lt;a href="http://www.uclouvain.be/epl.html"&gt;École Polytechnique 
de Louvain (EPL)&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.uclouvain.be"&gt;Université catholique de Louvain (UCL)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
He is a member of the ICTEAM research institute and is 
specialized in computer science.  His research are in artificial 
intelligence, constraint satisfaction and optimization. He is 
leading the BeCool Constraint research group.&lt;br /&gt;
Yves Deville is currently Senior Advisor to the President of 
UCL for the Digital University.  He is responsible for the development 
of the implementation of a comprehensive strategy for a digital university.&lt;br /&gt;
He is also President of the UCL IT Governance Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Education:  towards open digital learning resources
Yves Deville and Olivier Bonaventure, Université catholique Louvain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Short abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Education introduces, in the field of learning, an open approach 
with collaboration and knowledge sharing.  In terms of content, 
Open education proposes to promote the development and use of 
open educational resources, that is learning materials in a digital 
format freely distributed to educators, students or any individual 
around the world. Digital opens the door to new types of educational 
materials and facilitates dissemination. MOOCs are a possible 
implementation of the Open Education, but other digital technologies 
can also be offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the talk will present and discuss Open Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, &lt;a href="http://npettiaux.github.io/openForumBe/olivier-bonaventure.html"&gt;Olivier Bonaventure&lt;/a&gt; will present his experience 
with three open ebooks.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>